[snorts] War ravaging the East since
1937 and Japan's [music] invasion of
China
reached Europe on the 1st of September
1939 with Germany's invasion of Poland.
It became global on the 7th of December
1941 when Japanese aircraft attacked the
American naval base at Pearl Harbor.
It touched every continent
and lasted for six years.
It ended with a new weapon for a new
age.
This is the [music] history of the
greatest of all man-made events.
These men are part of that history. They
are eyewitnesses to the triumphs and
tragedies of the war wherever it was
fought.
Their testimony is part of the story of
how our world was made
by those who could pay
and those who could no longer meet
the [music] price of empire.
The new empires of East and West,
Japanese and German, had reached their
furthest limits in the course of 1942.
happened. There was in the minds of some
an extraordinary vision
that Japan spreading west would link
hands with Germany thrusting east. The
conquerors would meet in the Indian
subcontinent.
But as 1942 wore on, both Germany and
Japan would suffer setbacks, which
meant, as Winston Churchill was to say,
"If not the beginning of the end, then
the end of the beginning.
In May 1942, Japan's imperial ambitions
had been checked at sea. Battle of
Midway may not have turned the tide, but
it stopped the flood, and the tide
turned as the gap widened between the
abilities of the two sides to re-equip
and resupply.
The United States, which was to provide
the Grand Coalition with 75% of its war
material, demonstrated a remarkable
capacity to deliver to its armed forces
and its allies in apparently limitless
quantities.
It was said that America by 1943 was
producing a tank every 5 minutes, an
airplane every half hour, and an
aircraft carrier every week.
Germany had always known that the longer
the war went on, the more remote its
hopes of victory.
But on the 28th of June, 1942, hopes
were high. As we have seen, Plan Blue
launched against the weakest Soviet
troop concentration, the Southern Front,
the gateway to the Caucuses, made good
progress.
Stalin had been warned of the offensive
by British intelligence and by a
complete German battle plan taken from
[music] a downed German aircraft. He had
dismissed all these warnings as
misinformation.
Stalin waited for the attack on Moscow
to be renewed, but he got the plan that
Hitler favored and his troops fell back
in disarray, which encouraged Hitler to
make the call that many consider his
costliest error. He divided his force.
With the Crimea taken, he sent Army
Group A along the Black Sea coast,
aiming for the crucial oil cities of
Mop, Grozni, and Baku. Within 12 days it
had advanced more than 550 kilometers.
Hitler ordered army group B to advance
[music] on Stalingrad.
Foreign
speech. Foreign foreign foreign speech.
speech. Foreign speech. Foreign speech.
to the day.
In the initial bombing of Stalingrad, a
period of just 2 days, at least 40,000
Soviet citizens had been killed.
When the assault on the city began,
Russia's anti-aircraft guns had been
entrenched for use on the advancing
tanks.
The gun crews were almost all gun women
and they were almost all killed.
A million and a half Soviet women served
in the armed forces, around 490,000 of
them in frontline roles where they were
granted one benefit not available to
their male comrades, an additional 100 g
of soap.
On August the 19th, Army Group B began
its assault on Stalingrad. Within 4
days, it had reached the suburbs. What
could possibly go wrong?
Stalin's order number 227 simply said
that the Red Army was to stand its
ground. It said that retreat means
death. It worked.
Other measures announced by Stalin
helped. He reopened the churches. He
spoke of the sacred motherland rather
than the party. For the first time since
the revolution, officers were to be
addressed by rank and the role of the
political commisar was reduced to the
point of irrelevance.
In late August, Stalin appointed General
Guyorgi Zhukov, the 42-year-old son of a
shoe maker, deputy supreme commander,
and sent him to Stalingrad.
Stalingrad had been named Saritzin until
1925 when it was given Stalin's name to
commemorate his role in its defense
during the revolutionary wars.
The salvation of the city that bore his
name was a matter of personal pride for
the Soviet leader and its destruction
became a similarly illogical obsession
for the fura.
Levventi Beria the notorious head of
Stalin's secret police understood this
ego dimension. He described the battle
as a confrontation between two rams.
On August 23rd, Von Palace, commanding
the Sixth Army, the largest single
formation in the Vermacht, 290,000
strong, reached the river Vulga just
north of Stalingrad.
The next day, August 24th, Chukov
arrived in Stalingrad.
On September the 2nd, Hitler ordered
that when the city fell, the entire male
population was to be eliminated.
Stalingrad sprawled for about 40 km on
both sides of the vular and at a point
where that river was 1,300 m wide. By
the middle of September, Soviet defense
was concentrated on a garrison
restricted to the West Bank and to an
area little more than 15 km wide at its
widest point. The Germans had closed to
about 200 m from the river when at 1700
hours on the 14th of September, General
Alexander Rodimsef led the 10,000 men of
his 13th Guard's rifle division across
the Vulga and in a charge up the steep
river bank.
There were 320 survivors.
By the end of September, 9/10 of
Stalinrad was in German hands. It proved
not to be enough.
But jealous.
at the beginning of November. The
combination [music] of strengthening
Soviet resistance and the traditional
Russian ally winter halted the advance
by von's panser army into the caucuses
at Ojanitzi.
As the first ice appeared on the vular,
Marshall Zhukov and the rest of the
Stavka, the Soviet high command began
planning their counterstroke, Operation
Uranus,
designed to trap the German sixth army
at Stalingrad.
Russian army formations [music]
were known as fronts. General Vatutin's
southwest front would attack from the
north where it faced the Third Romanian
army.
The Stalingrad front, General Yerimeno
south of the city, also faced Romanians
as he drove north, linking with Vatutin
at Kalak.
The Dawn front was commanded by a
survivor of Stalin's purges who had been
tortured and twice subjected to mock
executions. His name was Constantine
[music] Roasovski. His task was to apply
pressure to Powus, preventing him from
responding to the maneuvering in his
rear. These Soviet formations
represented a land empire whose
population comprised
120 nationalities.
Ukraine.
foreign
[clears throat]
On the 11th of November 1942, [music]
the German assault on Stalingrad was
renewed.
A week later, the Southwest and Dawn
fronts began their attacks. The
Stalingrad front moved the next day. By
the end of November the 20th, Patutin
[music]
had advanced 40 km.
On the 22nd, he captured the bridge over
the Dawn and Kalak. And on the 23rd, the
Southwest and Stalingrad fronts linked
up just [music] as planned. Zhukov had
sent a million men, nearly a thousand
tanks, and more than a thousand aircraft
against the enemy.
330,000
Axis troops were now trapped in Deer
Kessle, the cauldron,
55 km by 30.
The Romanian Third Army had been
destroyed and the Romanian Fourth Army
crippled.
General Powus commanding the besieged
army estimated that he needed an airdrop
of 750 tons a day and Herman Guring
boasted that his Luft buffer could do
the job.
Of course, it could not. Guring retired
to the Ritz Hotel in Paris.
For Hitler, retreat or worse still,
surrender were not options. His only
order to the Sixth Army was to stand
fast.
On November 27th, Hitler created a new
formation, Army Group Dawn. He placed
[music] Fon Mannstein in command and
ordered him to relieve the encircled
Pace. At the end of November, the Red
Army launched new [music] attacks. A
week of heavy fighting forced von
Mannstein to postpone his planned
offensive.
Foreign
speech. Foreign speech. Foreign speech.
in the heart of the Russian winter. They
fought street to street, building to
building.
Roasovski said that the German army was
a machine and he said machines can be
broken. People are not machines, but
they too can be broken.
13,000 Soviet soldiers were executed for
desertion or cowardice during the
battle. They were forced to strip before
being shot so that their uniforms
destined for recycling would not contain
demoralizing bullet holes.
Morale was boosted by the performance of
Soviet weapons. The T34 tank based on an
offthe-shelf design by the American
Walter Christi was the equal of any and
the Kushia rocket launcher had no equal.
It was effective and it was terrifying.
Nine days later than originally planned
on December the 12th von Mannstein
finally launched Vintaga.
Winter's storm the offensive carried by
group Hot General Herman Hot went well
until it met fierce resistance at the
Mishka River and then the Soviet second
guard's army general Malinowski was
thrown in. Winter storm was turned back
and von Mannstein recognized that his
rescue mission had failed.
On December the 16th, [music] the
Soviets launched an offensive, Little
Saturn, against the Italian 8th Army,
which was wiped out.
Tatinskaya, the [music] main airfield
used by the Germans for resupply of
Stalingrad, was now in Soviet hands.
On Christmas Eve, the Stalinrad front
broke through the fourth Romanian army,
which had joined group hot and started
to swing towards the lower dawn. For
Mannstein withdrew group hot
I should
On December 28th, in view of the
deteriorating situation, Hitler
permitted two AR army groups to fall
back on the line Constantine of
Salcaria. They were now more than 200 km
from Stalingrad.
It was time for the end game.
On the 10th of January 1943, the Soviet
assault began.
Yeramno pressed against the east bank of
the Vular. An offensive perimeter formed
of six Soviet armies drew in like
[music] a drag net on the west bank. The
65th Army in the center pushed forward 8
km on the first day. After 2 days,
Roasovski's dawn front [music] coming in
from the city's southwest had lost more
than 250 tanks and taken 26,000
casualties.
By now, airborne resupply to the German
forces was down to 40 tons a day. By the
17th, the only airfield from which
supplies could be flown fell. On January
23rd, the last German aircraft flew from
Stalinrad.
A thousand years hence, Germans will
speak of the battle with reverence and
awe. Herman Guring said in a radio
broadcast on January 30th.
On that day, Hitler promoted Palace to
field marshal.
No German field marshal had ever
surrendered his command, and Hitler no
doubt expected the promotion to either
guarantee that Powus would fight to the
last man or commit suicide rather than
march into captivity.
A day later, January the 31st, 1943,
Gener Alfield Marshall Friedrich Von
Palace surrendered his command in the
southern pocket of the city to
Trickoff's 62nd Army. I have no
intention, Fon Powus said, of shooting
myself for this Bavarian corporal.
The Germans had a name for the sort of
fighting that had knocked down the
city's buildings. Raten Cree, they
called it, rat war. It produced legends
like the fighting at the tractor
factory, the grain silo, the main
railway station [music] which had
changed hands 15 times, and Pavlov's
house where Sergeant Pavlov [music] and
his unit had held out for 59 days until
relieved.
But even such heroics must in the end be
settled by the reality of modern war.
When the tractor plant was subjected to
a bombardment by artillery masked at a
density of 300 guns per kilometer, it
surrendered and the battle of Stalingrad
was over. It had lasted
199 days.
On February the 3rd, the Fura announced
the fall [music] of the city and
declared four days of mourning.
The official communicate [music]
announced that the entire Sixth Army had
been wiped out to the last man and the
last bullet.
In fact, 91,000 [music]
prisoners of war were marched through
the streets of Moscow.
5,000 would survive their captivity.
Following Stalinrad's surrender, German
radio played the Adagio from the seventh
symphony of Anton Brookner.
It would be played again in 1945
following the announcement of Hitler's
death.
From late in the winter of 1942,
German propaganda had been recasting the
war.
No longer a crusade to destroy Jewish
bulsheism,
it was now a life ordeath struggle
against the Asiatic Horde. In this vein,
the great orchestrator of German
propaganda made a landmark speech on
February the 18th.
Ysef Gerbles asks Vogen to
do you want total war? Do you want a war
more total and radical than even we can
imagine? Those listening on the radio
heard the carefully selected audience
respond fanatically.
They heard Gerbles end with a quotation
that Nazi leaders had used since 1920.
Now people rise up and let the storm
break loose.
[music]
The storm that had broken over
Stalingrad resulted in about 1,130,000
Soviet casualties.
Axis forces [music] suffered 850,000.
Stalingrad may have checked the tide,
but defeat in a battle is not defeat
[music] in a war, and the Soviet Union
had yet to expel a single invader from
its soil.
At the end of 1942, German troops were
in occupation of 14 sovereign states.
France, Belgium, [music] the
Netherlands, Luxembourg, Denmark,
Norway, Austria, Czechoslovakia, Poland,
Greece, Yugoslavia, Estonia, Latvia, and
Lithuania. [music] The Soviet republics
of Bello, Russia, and Ukraine were
occupied. Italy was an ally, and so too
were Hungary, Romania, and Bulgaria.
The Eastern Front remained a contest
between two great continental empires.
So, was Stalingrad decisive?
Like Midway, Stalingrad was a battle in
which both sides lost heavily.
But it proved that the German Empire was
not invincible. That Soviet generals
were at least a match for their German
counterparts. Above all, that the Soviet
Union alone was able to pay the cost of
exorbitantly expensive victories. It
would do so again at Kursk when the
Vermacht, still deep in Soviet
territory, would once again go on the
offensive.
What Stalingrad along with Midway and
the reversal of fortunes in North Africa
did do was persuade people on the Allied
side from the lowest to the highest that
they had turned the corner.
Ah,
>> this is not the end.
It is not even the beginning of the end,
but it is perhaps the end of the
beginning. [cheering]
Churchill was referring to the second
battle of Elmagne.
Through July and August, as we have
learned, RML was checked in North
Africa. His newly arrived adversary,
Montgomery, was first tested when RML
launched an offensive with, as his
objective, the British fuel depot. Fuel
supply to the Africa Corps was a
constant problem.
The key to RML's plan was a swing
against the Alam Ridge. He was beaten
back and in early September withdrew to
his start line.
Montgomery was determined to build up a
superiority in every type of arms before
rejoining the fight.
Some of the tactics were less than
orthodox.
Dummy tanks were positioned to persuade
observers that the attack was forming in
a certain place and real [music] tanks
were also disguised.
It was a framework on the outside of the
tanks with canvas on all painted to look
like a lorry. And it did look like a
lorry. And there's any number of tanks
behind the front line like this. Lorries
had been parked [music] in an area and
they'd pull out overnight. You'd pull in
overnight. And this this really fooled
the Germans quite a bit.
The second battle of Elamagne opened on
[music] the night of 22nd 23rd October
1942 with the first significant British
bombardment since the end of the first
world war.
>> The poor Germans they got they got it.
He opened up with over a thousand pieces
of artillery
on that other line that came by the way
like hailstones.
The line from which the offensive would
move stretched from the coast road south
to the [music] impossible Qatara
depression. 13th Corps General Horox at
the southern end of the line would push
against General Benvvenuto Joda's 10th
Corps.
The aim was to draw RL's armor south.
The main attack would be in the north
30th core. General Lee advancing through
minefields.
New Zealanders and South Africans fought
side by side on the southern end of 30th
cores advance. The New Zealanders
scoring an early success with the
capture of Miteria Ridge.
Up towards the coast, the advance of
9inth Australian division was slowed by
the minefield, as was the push from both
first and 10th armored divisions.
On the 25th, RML, who had been in
Germany for medical treatment when the
attack was [music] launched, arrived in
Africa and resumed command of the Africa
Corps.
Both the north and south thrusts of
Montgomery's attack stalled on the 25th.
The feared 88 mm anti-tank weapon was
particularly affected. The battle hung
in the balance.
The star shells flying everywhere and
all a lot of whistling going on. So the
the air was full of it.
If you dropped the ground every time you
had a whistling sound, you'd never get
up. For two days, blow and counter blow
were traded without decisive [music]
outcome. On the 28th, Churchill
expressed his anxiety. Plans for an
Allied landing at the western end of the
literal in [music] French North Africa
were about to be implemented and
advancing from the east [music] to
affect the linkup was vital.
On the 29th, Montgomery changed the
plan.
supercharge now had the Australian
division on the coast road as the faint.
The attack began [music] on November
2nd, 6 days before the landings were
scheduled for French North Africa.
Back I remember there was one tank
sitting out in front burning one of ours
and there's [music] a voice in my ear
saying help me.
The operator in that tank had been on
the wireless when his tank was hit
and somebody was trapped in that tank.
The wireless was still on.
God's sake, help me.
One of our tanks put a shot through the
side of it and the voice stopped.
That burns inside me. That does. I'm
sorry.
As supercharge began to bite into the
Axis lines, RML, whose forces were
desperately short of fuel and
ammunition, was obliged to withdraw.
The pursuit of RML across Libya began
[music] on November the 4th, and on the
10th, Churchill declared the end of the
beginning.
One morning, we saw a lot of burning
going on.
Another wrecky troop was sent forward
and came back the signal. Oh, it's it's
a general exodus.
In other words, the Germans are pulling
back. So, we chased them all the way up
the coast.
Second Elamine was clearly an Allied
[music] victory. The enemy was in full
scale retreat, but a sense of proportion
is necessary.
At the midpoint of 1942, there were
eight Italian and four German divisions
in North Africa. There were 12 and five
respectively [music] in the Balkans. 26
German divisions in Western Europe and
[music] 12 in Norway and
197 Axis [music] divisions on the
Eastern front.
Though Raml was on the run, he was
fighting with all the stubborn skill and
resource you'd naturally expect from
this general.
>> As the eighth army drove west in pursuit
of Raml, it may be said to have
represented the last hurrah of a once
great empire.
On the other side of North Africa, her
allies ground troops were entering the
war against Hitler under the supreme
command of General Dwight D. Eisenhower.
The Yanks were coming.
Operation Torch, the Allied invasion of
French North Africa, began on November
the 8th when landings in three places
met with strong French resistance.
These were forces loyal to the Vichy
French government.
>> There was a French Navy ship that start
firing at us. I believe it was the Vicki
French who opposed us and our battleship
sumped them at the pier
and all the troop ships
had their formation of landing craft
gathered together and they emerged onto
the beach.
A lot of the uh LCVPs that carried the
troops into the beach were unable to
dock
efficiently. So a lot of the troops with
their heavy armorament on them drowned
in the water because of the heavy weight
on his shoulder.
General Patton's western task [music]
force landed at three points on the
Atlantic coast of Morocco. The center
task force landed at Oran and the
[music] eastern west of Alers, both in
Algeria.
On November the 10th, Admiral Francois
Dalan, Vishih High Commissioner in
Alers, ordered an end to resistance to
the invasion.
Vichy Prime Minister Pierre Laval
hurried to Berlin to assure [music]
Hitler that Dalair had acted illegally.
But the Furer was not impressed and the
[music] next day he ordered German
troops to occupy the whole of France
bringing the pretense of the zone Libra
to an end.
He sent an explanation of his action to
the Vichy leader Philip Petan. It is to
be regretted, he wrote, that
unscrupulous Anglo-Saxons and primarily
Jewish wire pullers succeeded in
interpreting every consiliatory gesture
of the new Reich as a sign of weakness.
Hitler told Petan that insiters in Paris
demanded dismemberment of the German
Reich. He complained that they sought
the enslavement of the German people,
above all complete restoration of the
unrestricted right of plunder by the
Jewish race.
On the 11th of November 1942, the
anniversary of the armistice that had
ended the First World War, the French in
North Africa signed an armistice with
the Allies who began their advance on
Tunis.
which would hold out until April when it
became the jumping off point for the
invasion of Sicily
in the Pacific. Major campaigns were
changing the power balance of the war.
An archipelago of almost a thousand
islands, Solomon Islands is critically
positioned off the northeastern [music]
Cape of Australia. The Japanese called
the main island Gada Rukaru. The
Americans called it Cactus. Its name is
Guadal Canal. Japanese troops landed
there in April 1942 and [music] was soon
observed to be building an air base.
Such a facility could threaten mainland
Australia and naval [music] and combined
operations throughout the the theater of
war. On July [music] the second, the
American chiefs of staff ordered the
capture of Solomon Islands.
Little over a month later on August 7th,
American forces landed on Guadal Canal.
It was the first landing by American
forces in the Pacific and the first of a
series of island names to be indelibly
inscribed in American history.
The primary target of the Marines who
landed on Red Beach was the airirstrip
that the Japanese had been constructing.
When the Marines overran the airfield on
August 12th, they named it for one of
their number killed in action at Midway,
Major Loftton Henderson. Henderson Field
became the site of one of the bloodiest
of the Pacific battles.
The night after the initial landing, a
Japanese naval task force of seven
cruisers and a destroyer caught an
Allied force steaming through the 15 km
wide channel between Guadal Canal and
Savo Island, sinking the American and
Australian cruisers with the loss of
1,270
Allied seaman and 34 Japanese dead.
Following the battle of Tsavo Island,
the US Navy withdrew, leaving the
Marines on Guadal Canal without support.
But the Japanese allowed their
opportunity to pass, not bringing up
reinforcements until August the 18th.
The first Japanese counterattack went in
on August the 21st. They attacked at
night.
because they believed that Americans
being effeminate did not like fighting
at night.
900 men commanded by Colonel Ishiki
attacked at the battle of Tenaru River.
The Japanese were wiped out. The
Americans lost 35 men. Colonel Ishiki
committed Harakiri ritual suicide. And
it is said that crocodiles feasted on
the Japanese corpses.
Later in August, continuing naval action
in the waters around the Solomons swung
the advantage there back to the
Americans, whose fighters were by now
operating from Enderson Field. Supply to
Imperial Japanese Army troops on Guadal
Canal was thereafter limited to vessels
traveling from Bogenville at night. The
Americans [music] dubbed it the Tokyo
Night Express.
The next significant attempt to displace
the Marines was led by General
Kawaguchi.
The Battle of Bloody Ridge in
midepptember [music] was fiercely
contested. The Japanese were driven back
with 600 dead. The Marines lost 150 men.
By late September, Marine strength under
General Vandergrift had risen to 23,000.
The Japanese, recognizing the struggle
that they faced, sent [music] Lieutenant
General Hiukataki from Rabul with the
17th Army.
By mid-occtober, the Japanese [music]
had built their force to about 20,000.
The battle for Guadal Canal raged from
mid-occtober until the final Japanese
evacuation at the beginning of February
[music] 1943.
In the first two weeks of December, the
first US Marine division severely
debilitated by six weeks of fighting and
the depradations of tropical disease was
relieved by three marine divisions of
14th core General Alexander Patch. Patch
began offensive operations almost at
once and by early January, Japan
realized that its position on Guadal
Canal was not supportable.
Losses to hunger and [music] disease
were far outstripping losses to enemy
action.
Evacuation was ordered. The troops to be
taken to New Guinea.
By early February, 1,600 Americans had
been killed. As many as 32,000 Japanese
had [music] been lost to military action
or disease.
The Imperial Japanese Army had feared no
better during the parallel campaign on
New Guinea.
Now for a dispatch from the jungles of
New Guinea by an Australian newsre
cameraman just back from the front,
Damian Par.
>> It's an uncanny sort of warfare. You
never see a [__] even though he's only 20
yards away. They are complete masters of
camouflage and deception. I should say
about 40% of our boys wounded in those
engagements.
Haven't seen a Japanese soldier, a live
one. Anyway,
in July 1942, a small formation
comprising [music]
one Australian and one Papuan Infantry
Battalion was sent from Port Morsby on
the overland journey to Buuna on New
Guiney's north coast. Bruna had a small
[music] airfield which General Douglas
MacArthur determined he needed as a base
for further operations.
The small force that set off was named
for one of Sydney's better beaches,
Marubra force. Its journey lay along the
Cakakota track across the vertigenous
and densely jungled Owen Stanley ranges.
Marubra force reached the village of
Cakakota about the halfway point of the
track in mid July. Its orders from
MacArthur were to move on Buna at the
end of the month.
Frustrated by the battle of the Coral
Sea in their plans to take Port Moresby
from the Gulf of Papua, the Japanese
decided to approach overland.
A 2,000man advanced detachment under
Colonel Yosuk Yokayyama landed at Gona
on July 21st. Its orders were to make
for Kakakota.
The first contact between the Japanese
and Marubra force occurred two days
later.
The seventh Australian division was
dispatched to Papua in early August and
in the middle of the month, one brigade
began to move up the track.
The journey along Cakakota was a journey
into the malaria zone. And for every man
that was wounded, seven were
incapacitated by sickness.
Supplying troops on the track was also
problematic. In the 8 days it took
native bearers to reach frontline
troops, they necessarily consumed half
of the food that they carried.
2 days after the Australian 7th was
dispatched, the main Japanese force of
11,500 men landed at Buuna. By war's
end, 157,646
Japanese soldiers would have been sent
to New Guinea.
Barely 6% of them were to survive.
One important scene of action has been
Milan Bay. Our pictures show
reinforcements arriving after the
Japanese attempt to gain a foothold had
been broken by Australians.
There was contact made with the Japanese
for four nights when they would come and
set up a machine gun alongside of a tree
just across the uh the runway.
As fast as one would get killed there,
another would take his place.
They would do that for uh a number of
hours. In the meantime, we had troops uh
infantry over their side and gradually
they got the upper hand
and they left 88 dead.
There was a a Japanese that had been
machine gunned across his stomach and he
had both hands in there and the
uh pain or the agony was still on his
face.
You had to think of somebody's son,
somebody's father, and or somebody's
husband.
By September the 6th, the attempted
invasion of Mil Bay had to be abandoned.
Japanese troops were evacuated back to
Rabal. Milbay was the first outright
defeat of Japanese troops. Importantly,
it denied them the opportunity to
establish an air base. After two more
weeks of fierce fighting, the
Australians began to advance along the
Cakakota track.
Their objective, Buuna, fell to them
after weeks of vicious jungle fighting
in atrocious conditions of heat,
humidity, and disease.
In the Papua [music] New Guinea
campaign, the Allies lost 8,500
as battle casualties, the Japanese
12,000.
Both sides lost many more to disease.
Progress had been slow and [music] the
cost high, but the threat to Australia
had been removed.